GERHARD MARAIS

Madrid, Spain | (+34) 603 557 158 | <u>gerhard.marais1@gmail.com</u> | <u>www.linkedin.com/in/gerhardmarais</u> **European Union work permit holder**, South African

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

I am a pragmatic problem solver with ten years of experience in the Energy and Chemicals industries, and I am driven by a desire for continuous improvement and social upliftment. Problems energize me, and I achieve flow when I'm analysing symptoms, determining what's wrong, and developing solutions. I am thrilled to find an elegantly simple idea hidden beneath the surface. This drive compels me to learn quickly and act analytically. After identifying the root causes, I enjoy developing roadmaps and business cases with cross-functional teams comprised of diverse individuals in order to quickly eliminate problems and improve business processes.

People's development and upliftment are the most rewarding aspects of life. I started a social upliftment project in South Africa to serve my community. My leadership style is to coach and mentor while also setting a good example for my team. This tried-and-true work method has enabled me to consistently meet key company objectives.

I completed my MBA with a specialization in Finance in 2021 in order to broaden my financial knowledge and become a more well-rounded and globally relevant business leader. I'm looking for an opportunity to help shape the world's energy transition.

EDUCATION

IE BUSINESS SCHOOL MADRID, SPAIN

International MBA (concentration in Finance)

JAN. 2021 - DEC. 2021

- Dean's List (top 10% of all International MBA students)
- IE Africa Talent Collaboration Award
- Beta Gamma Sigma Honors
- Member of the IE Venture Capital and Private Equity Club and Music Club

UNIVERSITY OF PRETORIA PRETORIA, SOUTH AFRICA

Master of Engineering, Chemical Engineering (cum laude)

JAN. 2005 – DEC. 2010

- Studied lubricating properties of synthetic diesel (laboratory-based research and experimentation)
- Masters Level Courses: Advanced fluid mechanics, mechanical failure analysis and control system implementation

UNIVERSITY OF OKLAHOMA

NORMAN, UNITED STATES OF AMERICA

Winter Undergraduate Research Internship (Biomedical Engineering)

JAN. 2008 - MAR. 2008

• Converted a controlled gas chamber to test effects of changes in oxygen tension on wound healing mechanisms

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

EVOLUTION EUROPE (DEEP TECH INNOVATION & FUNDING | 70 EMPLOYEES) (<u>www.evolutioneurope.eu</u>)

MADRID, SPAIN

MBA Final Integrative Exercise (honours grade achieved)

SEP. 2021 - Nov. 2021

• Developed a strategy to restructure the company and improve its internal processes to increase monetisation of its services

EMZINGO | U (SOCIAL IMPACT & DEVELOPMENT | 40 EMPLOYEES) (<u>www.emzingou.com</u>)

SPAIN & SOUTH AFRICA

Social Impact Lab Fellow (excellence grade achieved)

JUN. 2021 - JUL. 2021

• Created a financial model, pitch deck and investment proposal for a venture in the Urban Farming sector in South Africa resulting in company attracting investment and executing their project

SASOL (CHEMICALS & ENERGY | \$12,3B REVENUE | 30,100 EMPLOYEES) (www.sasol.com)

SECUNDA, SOUTH AFRICA

Process Engineering Manager | Fischer-Tropsch Refining | Operations Support

FEB. 2020 - Nov. 2020

- Managed a team of 7 operations support process engineers
- Shifted my team's culture from plant support to continuous improvement and rapid execution
- Orchestrated the Refinery Improvement Forum and coordinated the execution of the program consolidating & aligning efforts of R&T, Operations, Engineering and Projects to build and execute a 5-year improvement plan with a value addition of approx. R750M over the period

Senior Process Engineer | FT Refining & Hydrogenation | Continuous Improvement

Jun. 2018 - Jan. 2020

- Led the implementation of a cloud-based digital twin solution for the UOP CCR Platforming unit the first in Africa
- Managed the Refinery catalyst portfolio and championed the Refinery Catalyst Forum, leading improvement initiatives of approx. R250M/annum
- Performed conceptual design for unit modifications to comply with for Euro V emission legislation
- Successfully organised training events for the Refining team with catalyst suppliers and licensors
- Coached & mentored multiple Engineers in Training through their 1st year of the Graduate Development Program
- Attained two Platinum Awards, awarded by the Senior Vice President for outstanding value addition

Process Engineer | FT Refining – Petrol & Hydrogenation | Operations Support

Oct. 2013 - May 2018

- Specialist in identifying and implementing efficiency improvement and emission reduction opportunities
- Performed technical and economic feasibility studies on improvement projects together with business case development for financial justification and technology selection
- Implemented multiple projects all the way from idea generation to implementation, incl. business case development, design, financial modelling, pitching for funding, project management and commissioning
- Experienced in project and construction contract management

Process Engineer | FT Refining – Tar, Diesel & Phenolics | Operations Support

JAN. 2011 - SEP. 2013

 Applied Lean Six Sigma methods with data analytics and modelling to improve process predictability and performance

START-UP AND ENTREPRENEURIAL EXPERIENCE

EMBA SWOP SHOP (www.embaswopshop.org)

Co-founder

SECUNDA, SOUTH AFRICA

FEB. 2013 - PRESENT

- Founded a plastic, glass and aluminium recycling upliftment project with 2912 registered users resulting in 282 tons of waste recycled and R484,000 worth of basic essentials delivered to the local community
- Represented the Secunda municipality in South Africa's Greenest Municipality Competition

CONTINUOUS LEARNING ACTIVITIES

- Lean Six Sigma Green Belt Certification
- UOP Advanced CCR Platforming Process Technology Training in Des Plaines, Illinois, USA
- Bloomberg Market Concepts (Certificate ID: 161462979032)
- Green Hydrogen | The fuel of the future (Certificate No: UC-98d294e7-69a8-40fb-8380-b69c8c92ea93)

LANGUAGES

English (fluent); Afrikaans (native); Spanish (A2)

VOLUNTEERING EXPERIENCE

ENACTUS (<u>www.enactus.org</u>)

JOHANNESBURG, SOUTH AFRICA

• Served as semi-final judge at the Enactus National Innovation Competition and the World Cup

2014 - 2020

IT SKILLS

Advanced proficiency in Microsoft Office, Power BI Analytics (dashboard development) and Minitab (statistics and data analysis)

PUBLICATIONS

Marais, G. and de Vaal, P.L., 2011, "Mechanisms of lubricated and unlubricated friction and wear," Proceedings of the ASME/STLE 2011 International Joint Tribology Conference, Oct 24–26, 2011, Los Angeles, California, USA

OTHER INTERESTING INFORMATION

• One Young World Ambassador

2013 - PRESENT

Summited Mount Kilimanjaro (highest peak in Africa)

2015

- Passionate musician & drummer, especially enjoy rock, blues, jazz and South African folk music
- Avid reader on the topic of history